TED:如何把自己变成化石
How to fossilize...yourself
Imagine being a fossil:
想象自己若成为化石：
touring the world's great museums,
在世界各大博物馆之间游走，
inspiring awe in onlookers of all ages,
使各年龄层的游客们都心怀敬畏，
posing for hordes of fawning photographers.
在大批殷勤的摄影师面前摆造型。
Sound like something you'd like?
听起来觉得还不错？
Well, good luck!
那么，祝你好运！
At least 99.9% of creatures that have ever lived
至少99.9%曾经存在过的生物
aren't preserved in the fossil record.
没能成为化石。
But forget about them,
不过不用管它们，
everyone else will,
因为剩下的都会成为化石，
and listen up!
仔细挺好！
If you want your corpse
如果你想要你的遗骨
in the exclusive 0.01% Club,
成为那0.01%，
the Hall of Preserved Fossil Fame,
进入名人化石保存室，
it will not be easy.
并不容易。
You better work!
你最好努力！
Step one: die.
第一步：死亡。
It's a cold, hard fact of fossilization.
成为化石的过程是冰冷无情的。
Everything paleontologists find
古生物学家发现的一切
was once alive and, at some point, died.
都是曾经活过，并且最终死掉的。
We'll skip the details
我们把细节跳过
and assume you had a long, fulfilling life
假设你拥有长久而幸福的一生
so we can get to what is really important --
然后再来看看最关键的部分——
how you die.
你怎么死的。
There are many ways to become a fossil,
变成化石的方式有很多，
so let's highlight your top death options.
我们着重聊聊那些高端一些的死法。
You could get yourself trapped in tree sap,
你可以将自己裹在树的汁液中，
which, when hardens, turns into amber
汁液会凝固变成琥珀
and can survive intact for millions of years.
可以完好无损的保存几百万年。
But unless you find a really big tree to sit under,
但除非你找到一棵足够大的树，
amber preservation will likely remain
不然琥珀很可能只会保存
the domain of insects and other very small animals.
昆虫和其他很小很小的动物尸体。
Generally, the right place to be
如果你想成为化石，
if you want to end up a fossil
一般来讲，最好的地方是
is wherever sediment is actively being deposited,
沉积物容易保存的地方，
like a lake or an ocean floor.
像湖底或海底。
A mountaintop or prairie?
山顶或大草原？
Not good!
不靠谱！
You need to get buried,
你要被埋起来，
the faster the better,
埋的越快越好，
because the longer you hang around on the surface,
因为你暴露在外的时间越久，
the more likely you'll get eaten,
就越可能被吃掉，
scavenged,
被捡走，
or otherwise destroyed
或者被破坏
before ever having a chance to get preserved.
在能够得到机会长久保存之前
If you can get buried someplace
如果你被埋在一个地方
with little to no oxygen,
一个缺少氧气甚至无氧的地方，
like a bog or a deep lake bottom,
像泥塘或者深湖底，
even better.
那就更好了。
That lack of oxygen will slow down your decay
缺氧会减缓你尸体的腐烂
and give you more time to fossilize.
给你更多时间变成化石。
So, let's say you're lucky enough to die
那么，假设你幸运地
and get buried in a shallow sea
死掉并且被埋在浅海
under muddy, sandy sediments.
在泥泞的、布满砂石的沉积物下。
What's your next move?
下一步干吗呢？
One option is a process
一种选择是经历
called permineralization.
所谓的石化过程。
While all your soft parts decay away,
伴随着你身上柔软的部分都慢慢腐烂，
your bones get saturated with mineral-rich waters.
你的骨骼充满富含矿物质的海水。
Bit by bit, microscopic crystals precipitate
渐渐地，这些海水中
out of these waters
凝结的微小晶体
to fill in the empty spaces and pores in your bones.
填充进你骨骼里的细孔。
Otherwise, you'd better hope
不然，你最好盼着
the sediments around you harden
在你骨骼渐逝时，
while your bones decay away
你周边的沉积物硬化
and another sediment or mineral fills in the spaces
有别的沉积物或矿物填充
your bones leave behind,
你骨骼留下的空间，
creating a perfect cast of your skeleton.
铸造成完美的骨骼造型。
Over time, the sediments around your fossil
久而久之，你身体化石周围的沉积物
will lithify or turn into rock.
将岩石化或者变成岩石。
But you're not in the clear yet!
但你还不是不能放心！
Many things could happen
这些沉积岩还会
to those sedimentary rocks
发生很多变化
that might destroy your chances
并且可能导致后人
of getting discovered.
没办法发现你身体变成的化石
They could get uplifted into a mountain range
他们可能因为地壳上升成为山脉
and eroded away
又被侵蚀流失
or carried along in an oceanic plate
或是随着大洋板块
and subducted back into the Earth's mantle,
潜没又进入地幔，
melting your fossil into hot mush.
将你的化石熔化。
Fingers crossed your rock surroundings
穿流过你周围的岩石
will get gently lifted up
会通过板块构造
by plate tectonics,
慢慢抬升，
sea levels will change,
海平面会变化，
and you'll end up under dry land
你最终会在干燥的陆面下
close to the surface,
接近地表，
but not so close
但又不是特别近
that erosion from wind and rain wipes you away
所以在你被发现之前
before someone can come find you.
表层的岩石被风雨侵蚀流失。
The last step in this long process,
这个漫长过程的最后一步，
an intrepid paleontologist has to come find you.
一位勇敢的古生物学家必须要找到你。
Maybe she's a research scientist
也许她是一名研究员
scouting for fossils your age and type
四处寻找你这样年龄和类型的化石
or just an amateur collector
或者只是业余收藏者
hoping for a fortuitous find.
期待偶然的发现。
She whacks away at layers of rock above you
她打碎你上面的层层岩石
or spots your fossil exposed
或者在河边经过一场洪水后
in a creek bank after a flood.
你化石的一部分露出来。
And there you are,
你就这样出现了，
a magnificent scientific discovery,
一个重大科学发现，
millions of years in the making!
经历几百万年的磨砺！
She and her colleagues gently extract you
她和她的同事们小心翼翼地
from the surrounding sediment,
把你从周围沉积物中取出，
measure and photograph
测量、拍照
all the bits and pieces they find,
对他们发现的一点一滴，
and begin the complex task of reconstructing
然后基于他们在你骨骼中发现的证据
how and when you lived
开始复杂的工作
based on the evidence they find in your bones.
重现你如何以及何时生活过。
Paleontologists will be some of your biggest fans
古生物学家会是你的一部分超级粉丝
along with all those admiring crowds at the museum.
还有博物馆里那些欣赏的众人。
You made it!
你成功了！
You spent years underground in obscurity,
你在地下默默无闻了那么多年，
shedding blood,
流血，
sweat,
流汗，
tears,
流泪，
and your internal organs.
失去五脏六腑。
You worked yourself to the bone
你努力到只剩骨头
until your bones disintegrated
直到你的骨骼分解
and were replaced by minerals and sediments.
被矿物和沉积岩取代。
But it was all worth it
当这一切都值得
because you're a famous fossil!
因为你成了著名的化石！
Now, you better hold that pose!
现在，最好保持那个姿势！